<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<study api_version="0.6">
  <id>307</id>
  <name>ZF_MrSol4000</name>
  <active>true</active>
  <user_id>41</user_id>
  <followers>
    <follower>
      <login>rnk</login>
      <email>rnk@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Ross Kettleborough</name>
      <id>41</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>ct2</login>
      <email>ct2@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Carlos Torroja</name>
      <id>263</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>eag</login>
      <email>eag@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Elizabeth Gibson</name>
      <id>80</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>dm6</login>
      <email>dm6@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Ding Minjie</name>
      <id>244</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>ob1</login>
      <email>ob1@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Oliver Beasley</name>
      <id>223</id>
    </follower>
  </followers>
  <managers>
    <manager>
      <login>sm11</login>
      <email>sm11@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Sophie Messager</name>
      <id>427</id>
    </manager>
  </managers>
  <owners>
    <owner>
      <login>rnk</login>
      <email>rnk@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Ross Kettleborough</name>
      <id>41</id>
    </owner>
  </owners>
  <!-- Family has been deprecated -->
  <family_id></family_id>
  <created_at>2009-05-14 09:26:34 +0100</created_at>
  <updated_at>2009-11-05 16:00:28 +0000</updated_at>
  <descriptors>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Alignments in BAM</name>
      <value>true</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Delay for</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the data release strategy for this study?</name>
      <value>open</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study name abbreviation</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP parent study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Please explain the reason for delaying release (e.g., pre-existing collaborative agreement)</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Are all the samples to be used in this study commercially available, unlinked anonymised cell-lines?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ArrayExpress Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA Policy Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding data release timing and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Study Accession Number</name>
      <value>ERP000110</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reason for delaying release</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Will you be using WTSI's standard access agreement?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Title</name>
      <value>Zebrafish Tilling by Illumina Sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Number of gigabases per sample (minimum 0.15)</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has this been approved?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Visibility</name>
      <value>Hold</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study contain samples that are contaminated with human DNA which must be removed prior to analysis?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Do any of the samples in this study contain human DNA?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study require y chromosome data to be separated from x and autosomal data before archival?</name>
      <value>false</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Project ID</name>
      <value>0</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study description</name>
      <value>The Zebrafish is becoming a popular model organism for developmental biology and human disease. This increasing popularity has resulted in a demand for reverse genetics, which has traditionally been neglected in favour of forward genetic approaches because of the lack of an efficient gene knockout (KO) technology. Thousands of phenotypes have been identified using forward genetic approaches, but time consuming positional cloning has slowed the identification of the genes involved. Morpholino oligonucleotides have become the method of choice for gene knockdown in the Zebrafish, but are restricted to early processes, and insertional mutagenesis has also become a popular method for gene led investigations. However, this still does not allow the targeted knockdown of genes of choice. More recently, zinc finger nucleases have been shown to be effective for gene targeting, but this method can be expensive and labour intensive, and is not seen as practical for the KO of hundreds of genes.
A project to sequence and finish (to 99.9% accuracy) the Zebrafish genome (one of only 3 vertebrate genomes to be completed to this accuracy, alongside human and mouse) has contributed to the effectiveness of a process termed TILLING, first described in arabadopsis and worm, to be used to create Zebrafish targeted alleles. This method traditionally uses cel-1 nuclease and fragment analysis to identify mutations, which is labour intensive and misses mutations, especially near SNPs, which are common. Here we show that by using re-sequencing, we are able to identify more mutations. Using this method we have screened 2 ENU mutagenised living libraries in 2 years, and identified ~200 KO. In total, the ZF Models Workpackage 4 collaboration has identified 243 Mutations in the Zebrafish, which will be publicly available via Ensembl, The Sanger Institute and ZIRC. In addition to identifying deleterious mutations in the Zebrafish, the Sanger Institute has committed to describing the phenotype of all mutations created during this project. Both morphological and molecular (by microarray or transcript counting on the Illumina platform) phenotypes will be described and published via ensembl and Zfin. 
The advent of next generation sequencing technologies has significantly changed the amount of mutations that can be identified and has opened up the possibility of identifying a non-sense allele in every protein coding gene within a reasonable time frame and budget. We have designed a strategy that will allow us to amplify and sequence thousands of exonic fragments on a single lane of the Illumina sequencing platform. A primer design program has been written that selects 100bp exonic fragments that are most likely to give a non-sense allele by ENU mutagenesis. These fragments (up to 4000 exons per experiment) are amplified across DNA pools from 24 mutagenised Zebrafish, and each pool is run on one lane of the Illumina platform. Automated data analysis then searches the sequence for all potential non-sense alleles in the amplified fragments, and putative non-sense alleles are confirmed by capillary sequencing. Using this method the Zebrafish Mutation Resource aims to produce &gt;1000 knockouts over the next 2 years, creating a rich resource for the Zebrafish research community.
</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>How is the data release to be timed?</name>
      <value>standard</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding prevention of data release and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has the delay period been approved by the data sharing committee for this project?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA DAC Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Abstract</name>
      <value>Target selected mutagenesis, or TILLING (for targeting induced local lesions in genomes), is a proven method that allows mutations to be identified in virtually any gene. We have previously shown that capillary-sequencing can be used to effectively identify mutations in a high throughput manner. A library of Zebrafish non-sense alleles is being created by the Zebrafish Mutation Resource, each with an associated morphological and molecular phenotype. Phenotypic data will be published via ZFIN (using an adapted version of the Phenote database). Information about the mutations identified by the project can be found on our website: http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Projects/D_rerio/mutres/.  
The advent of next generation sequencing technologies has significantly changed the amount of mutations that can be identified and has opened up the possibility of identifying a non-sense allele in every protein coding gene within a reasonable time frame and budget. We have designed a strategy that will allow us to amplify and sequence thousands of exonic fragments on a single lane of the Illumina sequencing platform. A primer design program has been written that selects 100bp exonic fragments that are most likely to give a non-sense allele by ENU mutagenesis. These fragments (up to 4000 exons per experiment) are amplified across DNA pools from 24 mutagenised Zebrafish, and each pool is run on one lane of the Illumina platform. Automated data analysis then searches the sequence for all potential non-sense alleles in the amplified fragments, and putative non-sense alleles are confirmed by capillary sequencing. Using this method the Zebrafish Mutation Resource aims to produce &gt;1000 knockouts over the next 2 years, creating a rich resource for the Zebrafish research community. 
</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the reason for preventing data release?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Type</name>
      <value>Resequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What sort of study is this?</name>
      <value>genomic sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reference Genome</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Faculty Sponsor</name>
      <value>Derek Stemple</value>
    </descriptor>
  </descriptors>
</study>
