<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<study api_version="0.6">
  <id>438</id>
  <name>Exon resequencing in patients with Brugada syndrome</name>
  <active>true</active>
  <user_id>129</user_id>
  <followers>
    <follower>
      <login>sls2</login>
      <email>sls2@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Solena Le Scouarnec</name>
      <id>299</id>
    </follower>
  </followers>
  <managers>
    <manager>
      <login>dw2</login>
      <email>dw2@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Danielle Walker</name>
      <id>86</id>
    </manager>
  </managers>
  <owners>
    <owner>
      <login>ajc</login>
      <email>ajc@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Alison J Coffey</name>
      <id>129</id>
    </owner>
  </owners>
  <!-- Family has been deprecated -->
  <family_id></family_id>
  <created_at>2010-01-26 15:17:28 +0000</created_at>
  <updated_at>2010-01-29 13:41:52 +0000</updated_at>
  <descriptors>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Do any of the samples in this study contain human DNA?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Faculty Sponsor</name>
      <value>Nigel Carter</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study name abbreviation</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Type</name>
      <value>Exome Sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Please explain the reason for delaying release (e.g., pre-existing collaborative agreement)</name>
      <value>Pre-exisitng RCA. Cleared by the Data Sharing Committee - 2.3.10</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has this been approved?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Title</name>
      <value>Exon resequencing in patients with Brugada syndrome</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding prevention of data release and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Delay for</name>
      <value>12 months</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Alignments in BAM</name>
      <value>true</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>How is the data release to be timed?</name>
      <value>delayed</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Abstract</name>
      <value>Sudden cardiac death (SCD) is defined as an unexpected, non-traumatic death occurring within one hour after symptom onset. It claims almost one million deaths annually in the USA and Europe and results most frequently from ventricular fibrillation. Among hereditary forms of SCD, Brugada syndrome (BrS) is described as a monogenic disease, transmitted in an autosomal dominant manner. A first gene, SCN5A, has been associated with BrS using a candidate gene approach but it is mutated in only 20-30% of the patients with a penetrance as low as 20-40%. In addition, a subset of SCN5A mutations can lead to the occurrence - in the same family - of BrS and other overlapping syndromes indicating the involvement of other genetic factors. Mutations involving other genes have been identified in patients with BrS, but their prevalence remains low (less than 1% of cases). 
The objective of this study is to identify new genes involved in BrS by screening for exon mutations across the whole genomes of 10 patients. The patients have been selected following 3 criteria: (1) each proband present with a symptomatic form of BrS; (2) only familial cases have been recruited, where at least three close relatives of the proband present with a similar phenotype; (3) for each patient, SCN5A mutations have been excluded by exon capillary sequencing. The data generated by this project will lead to the identification of new candidate genes involved in sudden cardiac death, which can be further tested for mutation in additional patients: (1) specific mutations detected in the probands will be assayed in the affected relatives; (2) more than 1,000 patients with BrS have been recruited to date through European collaborative networks: mutation screening will be initiated for each candidate genes on this larger cohort of patients, in order to further estimate their relative contributions to BrS.</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study description</name>
      <value>The objective is to identify new genes involved in Brugada Syndrome (BrS) by screening for exon mutations across the whole genomes of at least 10 patients with BrS. The patients have been selected following 3 criteria: (1) each patient presents with a symptomatic type I BrS; (2) only familial cases were recruited, where at least three close relatives of the proband present with similar symptoms; (3) for each patient, SCN5A mutations have already been excluded by exon capillary sequencing.
The recruitment of patients with BrS using these stringent criteria has been achieved by the &#8216;institut du thorax&#8217; in Nantes, France. DNA from the selected patients has been analysed by whole-genome exon capture and massively parallel sequencing. After DNA library construction, all coding sequences were captured in solution (Agilent Technologies) and the eluted fragments were sequenced using the Illumina technology. The data generated by this project will lead to the identification of new candidate genes involved in sudden cardiac death, which can be further screened for mutation in additional patients with BrS.
</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reason for delaying release</name>
      <value>other</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study contain samples that are contaminated with human DNA which must be removed prior to analysis?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has the delay period been approved by the data sharing committee for this project?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Project ID</name>
      <value>0</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What sort of study is this?</name>
      <value>genomic sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP parent study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding data release timing and approval</name>
      <value>Project will be assesed at the end of the 12 month period and data will be reviewed.</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the data release strategy for this study?</name>
      <value>managed</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the reason for preventing data release?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Will you be using WTSI's standard access agreement?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reference Genome</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Visibility</name>
      <value>hold</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Study Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
  </descriptors>
</study>
